Guide to the L. Auerbach and Brother records 1868-1880
Montana Historical Society
L. Auerbach and Brother records
1868-1880
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 125
L. Auerbach and Brother
3.5 linear feet of shelf space
L. Auerbach and Brother was a wholesale and retail store in Helena, Montana Territory, specializing in notions, liquor, cigars, etc. The firm was owned by Leopold Auerbach and his brother William Jacob Auerbach. Records (1868-1880) include a letterpress book of outgoing correspondence, ledgers, cash sales books, daybooks, journals, inventories, etc. There is also one cash book (1878-1879) for Auerbach, Wells and Company.
L. Auerbach and Brother, a Helena, Montana Territory, wholesale and retail company, sold stationery, notions, fancy goods, wine, liquor, teas, dry fruits, cigars, and tobacco. The firm was owned by Leopold Auerbach of San Francisco and his brother, William Jacob Auerbach of Helena, who managed the firm. Originally known as Auerbach and Greenhood, the name changed shortly after William Auerbach arrived in Helena around 1869. Other Helena companies of this period also bore the Auerbach name, including Auerbach, Wells and Company, and Auerbach and Klein. On June 28, 1880, William Auerbach was killed in a New York City train accident.
This collection contains the records of L. Auerbach and Brother, including William Jacob Auerbach's letterpress book (October 31, 1876-March 12, 1877), account ledgers, cash books, daybooks, a way bill register, bills of lading, a payment receipt book, store inventories, a wholesale supplier ledger, and a trial balance book. There is also a cash book for Auerbach, Wells and Company.
Arranged by subgroup and series. Some material housed in Manuscript Volumes. See inventory below for more information.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
L. Auerbach and Brother
Helena (Mont.)--Commerce
Liquor industry--Montana--Helena; Retail trade--Montana--Helena; Wholesale trade--Montana--Helena
Montana; Helena; Retail Trade
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- L. Auerbach and Brother
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Letterpress book, 1868-1877 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Financial Records
    - Account ledgers, 1868-1870, 1872-1874 (Box-folder 1 / 2-3)
    - Bank book, 1869 (Box-folder 1 / 3a)
    - Bills of lading (samples), 1875-1877 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Cash books, 1871-1877 (Box-folder 1 / 5-6)
    - Cash sales books, 1871-1878 (Box-folder 2 / 1-5)
    - Cash sales book, 1876-1878 (Box-folder 3 / 1)
    - Daybook, 1869-1870 (Box-folder 3 / 2)
    - Daybook, 1872 March - 1873 February (Volume 1)
    - Daybook, 1873 March - 1874 August (Volume 2)
    - Daybook, 1874 August- 1875 September (Volume 3)
    - Daybook, 1875-1876 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
    - Daybook, 1876-1877 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
    - Journal, 1870-1872 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
    - Journal, 1872 May - 1874 December (Volume 4)
    - Journal, 1875 January- 1880 March (Volume 5)
    - Inventory book, 1872-1877 (Box-folder 4 / 3)
    - Ledger, 1874-1875 (Box-folder 4 / 4)
    - Payment receipt book, 1869-1873 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
    - Trial balance book, 1875 April- 1878 February (Volume 6)
    - Waybill register, 1875 April- 1874 August (Volume 7)
    - Wholesale supply record book, 1876-1877 (Box-folder 5 / 1)
- Auerbach, Wells and Company
  - Financial Records
    - Cash book, 1878 March - 1879 October (Volume 8)